Human beings have been fighting. ing
over the Holy Land for thousands of
years,
leaving it covered in blood.
>> Today, conflict's been raging for over a
century.
Everyone says they want peace. So why
has no one delivered?
Who's right and who's wrong?
When I was young, I thought I knew the
answer to this.
My name is Jillian Mosley, and I'm from
a Jewish family with famous rabbis and
caners on both sides
and was raised in a Zionist household in
America.
I was taught that Jews have the primary
right to claim the Holy Land.
But I encountered another perspective in
my teens when I met Tamir in a
nightclub.
He was gay, apolitical,
and Muslim Palestinian.
I learned that most of his family's
property had been seized when Israel
became a state, despite their belief
that the Holy Land is their home.
My friendship with Tamir ruptured the
unquestioning entitlement to the Holy
Land that my family had instilled in me.
And I've struggled with this ever since.
When I look at Israel now, I see a mass
of contradictions, a tinder box liable
to ignite at any moment.
I just want the violence to stop. And I
think we urgently need to reset the
dialogue for peace.
So, I've decided to make this film while
I try to square the facts with the
increasingly emotional claims being made
today.
In a world where facts are often
replaced with opinion, how will we ever
reach consensus?
I want to lay out what I've learned
about how and why this conflict started
and at the same time explore the impact
of that history on lives of people
today.
Lots of attention is given to
extremists. But I hope by meeting
ordinary people from all sides of this
conflict, I'll learn from their
perspectives and see a way to move
forward, however uncomfortable that
might make me feel.
I've stayed away from Israel for the
past 10 years, uncomfortable with the
forces at work there, and I'm anxious
about what I'm going to find.
But I do know that this land of my
forefathers has become one of the most
contested places on Earth. From
rocket strikes and air strikes to
violence on the streets
>> and even after decades of mediation
everyone seems to have different ideas
about how to fix it.
>> I think we also recognize that
we have to find ways to change
uh the status quo.
>> We should all recognize the substantial
achievements that have been made.
One of the agreements that President
Sadat and Prime Minister Bean are
signing tonight is entitled A Framework
for Peace in the Middle East.
The United States will encourage a peace
and really a great peace deal.
We'll be working on it very very
diligently.
But it is the parties themselves who
must directly negotiate
such an agreement.
Does this land belong to the Israelis,
the Palestinians, or both?
And is that even the right question to
ask when the Holy Land is spiritual home
to three of the world's major religions?
Judaism, Christianity, and Islam.
Looking into this land's history, I
found the seeds of this current conflict
went much further back than I expected,
and that the catalyst was neither Jew
nor Palestinian.
I'm part British and proud as I am of
this heritage, I found British hands all
over the beginnings of this story.
As World War I raged, German allies
opened up a sprawling new warfront in
the east.
The British needed help.
So Te Lawrence or Lawrence of Arabia and
Sir Henry McMman, British High
Commissioner in Egypt, brokered a deal.
In exchange for troops, Britain offered
support for pan-Arab independence.
>> Great Britain is prepared to recognize
and support the independence of the
Arabs in all regions within the limits
demanded by the sheriff of Mecca.
Then with the Arabs on side, Britain
pursued further allies.
Many politicians believed in the global
power of Jews, but so did the Germans
who were rivals for Jewish support.
A bidding war was encouraged by a
prominent Jew who successfully lobbyed
top British politicians to offer and
then deliver bait.
return the Jews to their biblical
homeland.
But this biblical homeland was part of
the same territory earmarked for Arab
independence.
The catalyst for our present- day
conflict had emerged.
This motion was supported by Winston
Churchill as well as Prime Minister
Lloyd George and Arthur J. Balffor who
were both fervent Christians keen to
turn biblical prophecy into reality.
But some were wary of Britain's arrogant
kingmaking like former viceroy of India
Lord Keren.
I do not recognize that the connection
of the Jews with Palestine which
terminated 1200 years ago gives them any
claim whatsoever.
On this principle, we have a stronger
claim to parts of France.
>> This was all news to me. I'd been taught
that Israel was founded because of the
Holocaust, but it was actually global
interests converging decades earlier
that started the process.
Britain was prepared to promise anything
to recruit allies for the war and to
score Palestine as a staging post to
Egypt and India.
Britain's colonial policies seem to have
ignored common sense and indeed human
rights leading to decades of unintended
consequences.
And now with competing claims of
sovereignty, increasing violence on both
sides, and Jewish settlements on
disputed land on the rise, will we ever
find peace?
I've come to Israel to get to know
ordinary people from all sides of the
conflict, to understand how the
consequences of history impact their
lives today,
and to find out what they hope for in
their future.
I'm on my way to meet a Jewish settler
called Israel who lives about an hour
from Jerusalem in the West Bank and who
shares views with much of my American
family.
But I'm uncomfortable with the idea of
settlements which flout numerous UN
resolutions and never thought I'd visit
one.
We're here at Shilo. Shilo was where
Kana prayed for a son, where the
tabernacle was erected, where Joshua
divided up the land of Israel according
to the tribal portions. So, are we doing
anything wrong by returning to the land
of Israel? It's the most Jewish place I
could be that other people came here
later. It is a historical fact. Are we
able to share the land? I think Zionism,
even its more extreme wing, was always
willing to say this is a land for all
who live here. There's no problem about
Arab, Jew, Christian, Muslim living here
in the country as a citizen with full
rights. It just has to be understood
that in the Middle East where there are
now 24 25 Arab states, there's going to
be one Jewish one.
>> Israel Mad confounded my image of an
irrational settler. And as I'm finding
out, colonizing new lands is where
Britain went next in 1916.
In addition to World War I allies, ever
the colonialists, the British were also
after land.
Germany's Ottoman allies controlled much
of the Mediterranean and Middle East.
But before they were defeated, a secret
agreement was made to divide Ottoman
land between Russia, France, Italy, and
Britain.
This is when the idea that Britain
should govern Palestine and Trans Jordan
first took hold.
Although Jerusalem was to remain under
international mandate,
clearly even then dominion over
Jerusalem was sensitive.
I've driven 40 minutes through the West
Bank from Shilo to Ramala to meet Muna,
a Christian Palestinian.
>> Christians have been in the Holy Land
for over 2,000 years, an important part
of the Palestinian population now
decreased to around 2%.
They often get forgotten in this
conflict.
I used to hear my grandmother say, "I
just hope that your days are better than
mine."
>> But I cannot see that it's going to be
better with all that's going on in the
world.
>> Grace you and peace from God the Father
and Mother and our Lord Jesus Christ.
The preaching today is taken from
Revelation chapter 1. People
are being targeted. Nothing has stopped.
The settlements are still being built.
>> What's the point of negotiating peace
when it's not peace what they want? It's
a piece of land that they're after, not
peace.
I just feel that this is the safest
haven that I can be at. I just want to
live. I reached that point. I honestly
reached that point.
With Palestinian Christians suffering,
it was surprising to find out that
another group of Christians are adding
to the conflict.
More than 80 years before World War I,
around 1830, a Christian evangelist
called for Jews to return to Zion, now
Israel, to resettle their Biblemandated
homeland.
This evangelical support has now
mushroomed into the Christian Zionist
movement, which today gives Israel and
its settlements millions in annual
funding.
As a Jew, I have very mixed feelings
about Christian Zionist support because
according to their biblical beliefs,
once Zion has been established, Jews
will be wiped off the face of the earth.
Israel Mad doesn't agree.
>> I'm not upset about their
reasoning for their support.
There is a time for real politic
>> at stake, a homeland for Jews. And by
the late 1800s, after centuries of
persecution by the Christian world, this
call had unified politically under
Austrohungarian journalist Theodore
Herzel, who wrote that only through
gaining a Jewish state in their ancient
homeland could Jews escape rife
anti-semitism.
Jews could go to this land, but there
was trouble in paradise.
In 1891,
Ukrainian Jewish Zionist pioneer Aada
Arm went to Palestine.
The Jewish settlers treat the Arabs with
hostility and cruelty, trespass
unjustly, beat them shamelessly for no
sufficient reason. The Jews were slaves
in the land of their exile and suddenly
found themselves with unlimited freedom.
This sudden change has produced in their
hearts an inclination toward repressive
tyranny.
At the end of the 19th century, both a
and a fellow by the name of Epstein were
very much concerned when visiting
that the land was not empty. There was a
population here.
For them, it was like, "The bride is
beautiful." In other words, the land is
good, but she's already caught up with
someone.
Maybe we're not the proper groom.
With even Zionists like Aada questioning
a mass-cale Jewish move back to the Holy
Land, someone should have been paying
attention.
Palestinians were already living here.
How could this ever end? Well,
>> I wanted to talk to a political activist
and met Issa in Hebron in the West Bank.
Although it's only 26 miles from Ramala
where Muna lives. It took us 2 hours to
drive here because of checkpoints and
road diversions.
Straight up up, you know, then you reach
the the exit of the city.
I am a human rights uh defender in the
city of Hebron. I try to make my people
believe in nonviolence resistance and uh
civil disobedience.
I was afraid of soldiers, you know. I
had to fight my fear to be able to just
pass a checkpoints. I just felt them
expanding the the settlement. This is a
an infamous settler woman. She's
expanding her house to the street and
building a new uh outside uh room. So I
called the lawyers who will call the
Israeli civil administration and call
the Hebra Municipality and we'll call
the Israeli police to try to stop that.
Usually it's not easy because you know
they are under the civil law and they
give them free hands to do whatever they
want. But what she's doing and what they
are doing there, it's 100% illegal.
>> Why is it illegal?
>> First, it's in the street. Second, the
house is owned by a Palestinian family.
It's not owned by the Israeli settlers.
Third, they don't have any permission
from Hebrew Palestinian municipality
which is responsible about what is
happening. And look, they're running.
They are trying to to make it fast. And
the Israeli army sees that, but they
don't stop them. There is no political
will to stop them.
My first visit to Hebrron, where fewer
than a thousand Jewish settlers live
under armed guard in the heart of a city
of 200,000 Palestinians, shocked me.
I headed to Jaffa next. Once a
Palestinian city, it's now melded into
the metropolitan city of Tel Aviv.
I was here to meet Kobe, the Jewish
frontman of Israeli metal band Orphan
Land, who uses their music to champion
coexistence.
>> Everything with the band started to give
me a lot of meaning to my life.
Orphaned land.
seeing that place which is described as
a holy place or a promised land to the
Jews.
>> What's so holy if blood is spilled all
over this place?
That's why we've decided that this place
is more some kind of an orphaned land.
As an artist, you start to question
yourself if you are true and authentic
and you start to get your opinion
yourself not only based on the media.
We've started to write these songs from
a place where we stand in the middle and
we don't take sides using elements from
all these Middle East and the result was
amazing because we have fans who are
Israelis who are even settlers or
religious orthodox Jews and then on the
other hand we have fans who are Arab
Muslims who lives in Gaza.
I think that I was attacking politicians
or religious priests many time in our
albums, but this time we attack the
people themselves.
>> Because Albert Einstein once said, "The
world will not be destroyed by those who
do evil, but by those who do nothing
about it." Most of the people, they're
not terrorists, they're not bad, but
they just don't care. You just go home
to watch Big Brother, to watch TV, to
read about Kim Kardashian's ass.
I feel Kobe has a point, and I'm not
sure how many people do care, but with
tens of thousands dead and millions
displaced, can we afford not to?
The Holy Land is the birthplace of
Judaism,
but most Jews were forced to leave
during the Babylonian and Roman
conquests.
And by 1917,
while small numbers of Jews had returned
over centuries,
most were content to remain in the
diaspora.
I can understand this as my ancestor
immigrated from Germany to England in
the early 19th century, changing his
name from Moses to Mosley.
While on the other side, we'd come here
from Spain and Italy in time for
Reverend Meldda to become an early chief
rabbi in London. and my family have
integrated and still live here happily.
But at the same time in Russia and
Eastern Europe where persecution raged
and amongst the working classes, Jewish
Zionism flourished.
The word Zionism now means support of
modern Israel, but was defined as an
international movement for the
establishment of a Jewish national or
religious community in Palestine.
Alongside, anti-semites from Russia to
America and Britain saw Zionism as an
opportunity to get rid of their Jews.
which meant there was considerable
support in 1917
for British Minister Arthur Balffor
who was about to make a declaration that
would change history.
When I was 12 years old, there was the
first time I was confronted with
demonstration. As a child, I was really
confused. That was the first time that I
realized that something was going on
that is way more than my understanding.
It kept coming back into my mind until I
realized what it meant. It was
demonstration against Balfur
declaration. But I never knew who Blefer
was.
>> His Majesty's government view with favor
the establishment in Palestine of a
national home for the Jewish people. It
being clearly understood that nothing
shall be done which may prejudice the
civil and religious rights of existing
non-Jewish communities in Palestine. All
the rights and political status enjoyed
by Jews in any other country.
For Zionists, support by a world power
was a gamecher,
one they'd lobbied hard for.
In his letter to Lord Rothschild sent
just 2 years after Britain pledged Arab
independence, Balffor promised a Jewish
home in a country that was 90% Muslim or
Christian.
And this commitment was tabled just as
Britain's previous agreement with the
Arabs was about to pay off.
Alan's army followed the route of the
ancient Egyptians up the plains from
Gaza. And on the other side of the
Jordan, the Arabs under Lawrence and
Fisel moved up in support. And in 1917,
Jerusalem itself was captured.
Following General Alen's historic
victory over the Ottomans, Colonel Sir
Ronald Stores served as military
governor of Jerusalem, but he was deeply
concerned by the Balffor Declaration.
The declaration took no account whatever
of the actual inhabitants of Palestine.
This was not the first time the country
had been colonized.
Yet again, the peoples of Palestine had
been denied the chance to rule
themselves independently.
We are so tired and so abused not only
by the British but by the Ottoman and
then the Israelis.
Yes, I'm angry because they cannot give
what's not theirs to others. Um, you
cannot promise what's not yours.
But promising land that wasn't British
was exactly what Britain did. Although
this fact and others seemed to have
largely been forgotten.
I was raised to believe in the mighty
intellectual heritage of Jews. one
that's propelled us time and again to
great success. But what I've found is
willful ignorance on a scale that's
caused me to question this key part of
my own identity.
First referenced by Heroditus in the
fifth century BC,
Palestine came to include what's now
Israel.
But one British Jew I encountered was
adamant that a place called Palestine
never existed.
And although Israel Midad, a settler,
admits that there was an Arab majority
in this country when General Alenbe
arrived, one Israeli I spoke to thought
these numbers were made up. An
international conspiracy, no less.
To be fair to both, they've clearly been
educated to believe this. And in an era
of fake truths, there's certainly plenty
of misinformation around.
The perfect formula of brainwash is
first they sell you half of the truth.
There's a war in Israel and Gaza and
then you see riots in Paris. And
everyone tells me, "How would you go to
Paris with those riots?"
We go to Paris and 500 people come to
the show, mostly Arabs, and they give me
only gifts.
But the news don't tell about these
people.
The second way to brainwash people is
with people who have a lot of charisma.
Could be your imam, could be your rabbi,
could be your prime minister.
They know how to manipulate you with
their charisma. You cannot argue with BB
Netanyahu. His rhetoric ability to speak
and to convince. It's amazing.
He can hide his idiotic agenda behind
those words and not only him.
But it's not only fake news that
undermines the potential for peace here.
It's also the fragmentation of its
communities.
In 1917, the Palestinians did not have
their own access to Britain's corridors
of power. But worse than this, they were
unable to unify with different families
controlling religious and civil
administrations.
While Christian Palestinian progressive
education pioneer Khalila Sakaini could
only comment from the sidelines.
Yesterday they fed over the Ottoman
government and today they fed over the
English government. We have a place. We
have a language. We have a culture.
Independence. Independence.
>> In 1919, a commission was convened to
ask what Arabs wanted. Most preferred
American rule under President Wilson,
but he died giving Britain the mandate
of Palestine as suggested four years
earlier.
British double dealing and global
interests paved the way for Zionist
success and worse was yet to come.
From the start of the mandate, British
officers complained that Zionists had
their own agenda.
Diaries show that the mandate was
severely underfunded and understaffed.
With the Great War just over, turning
Palestine into a Jewish home was likely
not a British priority.
So Zionists took free reign.
The global Jewish community was sending
charitable monies to support immigrants.
Support that continues to this day.
And WF Sterling, governor of Jaffa,
witnessed Zionists pushing change on all
fronts.
Palestine was officially a triilingual
country and every public notice had to
be issued in three languages.
But since the bulk of the Jewish
colonists did not understand Hebrew,
they had to sit down and learn their
supposedly native tongue.
>> Language and religion were not the only
dividers.
Sterling also witnessed potentially
explosive culture clashes.
The Jews who had little or no
inhibitions thought nothing of the
practice of mixed bathing in the nude.
The Arabs with their strict rules of
sexual conduct regarded behavior such as
this as the very negation of elementary
decency.
>> On the one side were the Arabs of
Palestine whose case was strong and
Zionists knew it.
If the arithmetical conception of
democracy were to be applied now, the
majority that would rule would be the
Arab majority, and the task of
establishing and developing a great
Jewish Palestine would be infinitely
more difficult.
Zionism's clash with the democratic
process leaves Palestinians today
feeling undermined and under represented
while Jewish claims to the Holy Land get
louder.
>> Israel is the Israeli state since ever
since 3,000 years ago 3,500 years ago.
One of the things that we know about our
uh families that it has been mentioned
in different places from the 1400s and
1300s.
>> I realized very very clearly from the
Torah, the five books of Moses, the
beginning of the Bible, that it is the
will of God for Jews to live in the land
of Israel.
>> My family is uh 10 or 11 generations uh
living in Nazareth.
>> My family came from Hebron. We've been
here 20 plus generations.
Clearly, the Jewish community is
unimpressed with the length of these
Arab families residence in the Holy
Land.
The Jewish claim going back to the Bible
itself is surely far stronger.
This is certainly what many Jews,
including me, are raised to believe.
But is it true?
Israelites were first recorded in 1202
BC
and archaeology also shows two periods
of ancient rule.
The land could theoretically belong to
the Canaanites if there were any today.
Yes. invaders, yes, conquerors, but no
one stayed and no one gave it a life, an
identity of its own except for the
Jewish people. And that's why, in my
opinion, we have a primary claim to be
the people, to be identified with the
national homeland, which is called the
land of Israel.
Kelshil is an amazing place. It just
shows you in a very small area what this
country is about in terms of its
historical continuation.
All peoples, all religions, all types of
cultures are all to be found here. So
for us, it says yes, we were here. This
is our land.
>> What is the specific evidence linking
this site to the Jewish people?
>> Our culture is mirrored in the ground.
walls that we know with pottery or arrow
heads or jewelry from that period of
time. So we can establish a time period.
We cannot establish a specific person
who lived in or something else like
that.
>> If we're using the Bible to justify
this country as a Jewish homeland, but
the Bible itself is not entirely proven,
there's a disconnect.
There is no disconnect.
I do believe that everything in the
Bible
as much as possible has either been
proven or according to what we've seen
develop will be proven within
the realm of more than just a
possibility or even a probability. How
accurate, I'm not going to be holding to
>> to my secular mind. The fact that the
Bible may be proven in the future is not
proof.
Some Jews are after all using it as a
land deed.
If you remove this from this area, if
you deny us the return to this country,
we have no holidays, we have no customs,
we have no literature, we are nothing.
And here we are at the nub of the issue,
an existential angst shared by so many
Jews that without the land of Israel, we
are nothing.
Existential versus a practical claim on
the land.
For me, like any Jew raised Zionist,
this is very murky territory. And it
gets worse.
Like most Jews today, I don't live in
Israel. But why is this if Israel is so
important to our collective identity?
I have to ask,
is a Jewish state our only way forward?
>> For some, like Kobe and his Palestinian
friend Abbed, coexistence is still
possible.
>> When you have a friend or when you have
someone who is like your brother, me and
Abbed, we always fight each other. Who
will pay the bill? I will pay the bill.
No, it's my turn. I want to pay the
bill. You are my guest, I will pay. So
brothers, they don't fight. No, this is
mine and not yours. This land is mine
and not yours. It's the other way
around. Everything that is mine, it's
yours.
That's the true peace. That's the true
brotherhood. The true peace that can be
achieved. The only way to make peace is
like that.
touring with orphan land was a lot of
fun. People always wanted to interview
us because, oh, you're an Israeli and
he's a Palestinian and you're like
brothers and family. But that's how it
been. It's like today going to the US
and asking a white guy, oh, do you have
any African-American friends? And doing
like, you know, an item about, oh, this
is this white guy will have an
African-American friend. Like, what
you're talking about? This is the norm.
But is peace and harmony actually
achievable now when the Balffor
Declaration sparked violence so long
ago?
Following the declaration, Ukrainian
revisionist Zionist leaders Evabotinski
began importing weapons illegally and
training Jews in warfare.
We're going to Palestine first for our
national convenience and second to sweep
out thoroughly all traces of the
oriental soul.
>> Another young Zionist, David Bengorian,
was also rising fast.
>> There is a national question here. We
want the land to be ours. The Arabs want
the land to be theirs.
But as David Benorian articulated the
basic problem, the Zionist cause was up
against an unshakable fact. When the
British arrived in Palestine, Muslims
had ruled these lands for over a
thousand years.
By 1920, a serious clash was inevitable.
Violence at the Muslim Nebi Musa
Festival was a watershed with Harareet's
newspaper reporting there had been no
clashes like these for hundreds of
years.
Palestinian nationalist Khalila Zakini
took the uprising more personally.
The fer almost turned into madness. I
went to the municipal garden, my soul
disgusted.
Military Governor Ronald Stores was
blamed for not being prepared and
Britain replaced Palestine's military
administration.
On the 30th of June 1920, the first
Jewish high commissioner, Herbert
Samuel, signed a receipt for one
Palestine complete.
Zionists considered the appointment of a
Jewish high commissioner a win, but
peace was short-lived.
At the Mayday parade in 1921,
Jaffa's governor WF Sterling had a front
row seat.
>> We had serious riots in Jaffa. Jews were
shot and stabbed in the narrow lanes of
the town and Arab women joined in the
attacks on Jewish colonies. Atrocities
were committed by both sides and some
Arab women lying wounded in the fields
were seen to have their breasts sthed
off by the Jewish colonists. Troops were
eventually rushed up.
Called an orgy of pillage as ring
leaders were brought to justice.
Zionists were angry with Herbert Samuel
for treating Jews and Arabs equally.
Samuel faced a horrifying thought.
Nothing would be worse than if it were
to appear that the one thing the Jewish
people had learned from the centuries of
their own oppression was the way to
oppress others.
>> Like Aada Samuel felt uncomfortable with
the idea that Jews had turned from
victim to oppressor.
Dozens of biblical teachings that tell
Jews not to oppress strangers seem to
have been repeatedly ignored.
And this upsets me, chipping away at the
moral pillar which to me lies at the
very heart of Judaism.
My great-g grandandmother was called
Katherine Samuel.
And I've often wondered whether she and
Herbert were related.
During my research, I found out that in
fact I'm related to all the British Jews
in this story.
Have I inherited their responsibility
for this saga?
In Samuel's Palestine, the Jewish
population had increased by more than a
third over 5 years.
Back in Britain, there were escalating
questions in the House of Lords. Had the
mandates policies created a monster?
Zionist home must and does mean the
predominance of political power on the
part of the Jewish community in a
country where the population is
predominantly non-Jewish. The Jews in
Palestine have lived in the past in
harmony. The whole agitation has come
from outside from Jews in other parts of
the world.
To sum up, in 1915 we were certainly to
have an Arab state. In 1917 we were to
have a Jewish national home. In 1918, we
were to have a self-governed Arab state
under British guidance. But in 1922, we
come back to a Jewish state.
I was surprised at how extensively the
Palestine question was debated in our
parliament because British politicians
today seem to have forgotten they were
ever part of it.
Even when numerous misgivings proved
prophetic,
>> Zionist colonization must either stop or
else proceed regardless of the native
population, which means that it can
proceed and develop only under the
protection of a power that is
independent of the native population
behind an iron wall which the native
population cannot breach. That is our
Arab policy.
With powerful British ministers favoring
Zionists,
this policy would come back to haunt
Britain,
setting the scene for today.
Israel is a state that's basically built
on making anyone who is not Israeli and
I want to say in this case also not
white feel very very very um
insignificant.
>> I'm not a secondass citizen. I'm a human
with with rights and dignities.
>> The other side need to acknowledge your
existence. They need to acknowledge us.
But erosion of Palestinian rights and
influence really began as land first
started to change hands in the 1920s.
Zionists were eagerly buying land with
Arab land owners selling willingly if
often in secret.
Muslim Palestinian nationalist Anoir
Nusebe, grandfather of my friend Tamir,
saw the inevitable pain.
Every acre of Arab land once it is taken
over by the other side becoming
inalienably and forever the property of
the other side that you cannot buy, that
you cannot lease, that you cannot work.
Well, gradually people felt that they
were pushed out inch by inch
from their heritage, from their soil.
This battle for the land still touches
the lives of everybody I met.
When I was a teenager, even though I
grew up in Jaffa and I know the stories
of coexistence, I got brainwashed from
the media.
It's strange to talk about it, but I
remember at one point I said, "I have to
do something.
If it's not to put my fist on an Arab's
face, then I have to do something." And
I just did this graffiti and I wrote
death to all Arabs.
>> When I was just 6 months old, the six
days war broke and my mom and dad had to
uh flee us all and we stayed in the
caves.
>> In 1948, rumors were spread. Young women
were raped or taken away. land was
confiscated. So people were scared from
from these things.
>> The year 67, I was here during the war.
In fact, I spent the week of the war in
a foxhole.
>> Everyone I've met on this journey seems
to have been affected by these
historical cycles of violence. No one
more so than Issa.
>> During my childhood, uh the Ibrahim
massacre happened just few meters from
my school.
He killed 29 Palestinians and hundreds
were were injured.
>> The massacre of Palestinians in 1994 by
a Jewish settler was a tragic echo of an
incident that had happened 65 years
earlier.
In 1929, a police superintendent
witnessed an Arab in the act of cutting
off a child's head with a sword. On
seeing me, he tried to aim the sword at
me, but missed, and I shot him low in
the groin. Behind him was a Jewish woman
smothered in blood.
1929, we had a massacre in Hebron
against the Jewish community here. And
uh we are not proud of that massacre.
With the Hebrron massacre, a violent
watershed had been passed for the second
time, and the situation was about to
explode.
I don't want to be pessimistic, but it
seems to me that everything is getting
worse.
In the past, there was a bus from Gaza
to Tel Aviv, but now it's impossible to
do it. It's impossible to do it today.
There's more checkpoints on our side.
There's more Hamas on their side. the
weapons in Gaza and in Israel, it's much
much
bigger.
>> I think the hate is even bigger.
I think the fact that social media is
now a part of our life, everyone has a
microphone today.
I can see Jews, Israelis that say should
wipe all Gaza, just throw a nuclear bomb
on them. You can hear Arabs who say,
"Too bad that Hitler didn't finish his
job."
As I've been traveling, I've become
increasingly aware of the enforced
separation between Israelis and
Palestinians and I'm frustrated as this
fuels mistrust and fear of the other.
It's complicated because they do have a
very uh complex style of living that is
very different and very um not western I
would call it and not democratic.
Israeli soldiers were conducting a
training how to arrest violently a
Palestinian. It's a kind of harassment.
It's not kind of security because people
will not reach here without passing a
metal detector and another checkpoint.
And the kids were afraid. They thought
that something wrong happening. So I
told them it's only a training. But
Palestinian children in this
neighborhoods, they don't know what is a
training and what is real. So they are
always terrified, intimidated to walk
around or to go to their school. I
didn't know how bad the situation was in
Palestine until I lived in the US during
my years in college because we are
normalized to think and believe that
this is okay and that we are secondass
citizens. Um and so when I went to
Pitzer I was like oh there's a pool uh
we have access to water all the time.
Okay, we are citizens of Israel. But
there is a lot of difficulties
also about our rights. You know in my
village there is 1,000 h houses or
homes. They don't have electricity. Many
times I find myself uh thinking about
how it is that I live in such a
privileged um safe uh liberal bubble and
around me there is occupation and there
is uh people suffering and there is uh
poverty and uh lack of human rights
from the 1930s. Human rights were on a
collision course with the authorities as
the British cracked down to suppress
increasing Jewish and Arab gang violence
within 14 years. And with US and UK
immigration now capped, the Jewish
population more than tripled.
And there were more than 10,000
incidents in Palestine over 16 years.
Around 2,000 Arabs, Jews, and Britons
died.
>> Either people will suppress their anger,
which will make them go mad, or they
will rebel, and plus it beautiful
Palestine will become a land of
insurrections.
The Arab revolt from 1936 to 1939
claimed yet more lives as violence
escalated with the British deploying
anti-terrorism measures.
This is the extent to which that people
were able to express their resentment at
being neglected, their destiny being
controlled by forces which are
completely outside themselves, in which
they had no say at all and which they
felt would ultimately result as it did
in fact in their complete non-existence
as a people on their country on their
soil.
Today, these now entrenched patterns
have seen the Palestinians contained in
ever smaller pieces of land and has
become a full-blown occupation.
>> I think occupation is a big issue. I
don't think there is a way to make uh
occupation moral.
This contradicts another belief that I
encountered amongst some Jews, namely
that there is no occupation.
But what does this occupation actually
mean?
Palestinians in the West Bank are
governed with different laws from
Israeli Jews.
Here they live under military rule with
strict controls on their movements.
the political situation between Israel
and Palestine and it is a political it's
not a religious situation
uh is affecting our everyday life.
My extended family lives in Bejala and
if I want to go and visit there I have
to pass two three checkpoints at least.
My sister, she has a residence of Gaza
and she can't come to Ramla because Gaza
people cannot come unless they have a
special permit. So for me to see my
sister, we have to meet in Jordan.
The state of Israel grants a higher
legal status for somebody who was born
for a Jewish family in Palestine and the
same time grants or maintains an
inferior status for a Palestinian living
under Israeli control.
I'm one of the very few lucky people who
has a job in Palestine at this age.
I have to go through Colia checkpoint
every day to cross through and cross
back. I have a permit. I was born in
Jerusalem, but I was never able to go to
Jerusalem until I got this permit for
this job through this international NGO.
Not because I was born there, not
because I'm Palestinian. nothing to do
with me being equal to any other Israeli
citizen who has access to that place.
The treatment there every morning, the
way the checkpoint is designed is to
make you feel like you are worthless.
It's hard not to feel empathy for these
people,
but some feel these restrictions have
come about out of necessity.
A checkpoint means I want to make sure
you have carry nothing that would kill
someone. It's not there to say, "Okay,
stand in line, get on your knees," or or
any sort of other discriminatory or
inhuman behavior. It's not there simply
because we don't like Arabs. It's
because we don't like violence done
against us.
After independence in 1948,
Israel was surrounded by conflict and
open warfare that challenged the
country's right to exist as a Jewish
state.
In the 60s and 70s, some Palestinian
groups perpetrated terror
internationally.
During the second interif, suicide
bombings became common with Islamic
groups like Hezbollah rising.
Israel and the PLO signed letters of
mutual recognition in 1993.
While only some Hamas voices accept a
transitional Palestinian state.
Hamas is viewed by some as terrorists,
some as freedom fighters, and some as
crucial to delivering desperately needed
social services.
And while Palestinian Arab violence
against Israelis has decreased
significantly since 2005,
the exceptions are hardcore Islamic
groups, including Hamas, which continues
to fire rockets and other incendurary
devices.
The Israelis have always fought back,
some say with disproportionate force,
also initiating their own attacks and
annexing further land.
This conflict has turned into an
epidemic of fingerpointing.
How would things be different today if
we could have learned during the mandate
that this would only fuel fear, hatred,
and violence?
I'd been focusing on the West Bank, but
my Jewish friends and family kept
pointing fingers at Hamas, who they
blame for the entire conflict.
So, I went to the Gaza border, where I
found contradictions.
>> I feel sorry for them. I feel all the
time. My heart is it's for them because
I know that they they they suffered.
>> Of course, it's all Hamas's fault. Kamas
could have started they got all the
money from UNRA. They got all the money
from the United Nations, from the EU.
They could have made in in in Gaza like
a the best city in the in the Middle
East. But you can see it's like it's the
mentality.
>> I am bling a lot of the problem with
Gaza. It's not only the Israeli
politics, also the problem of their
politics.
>> Somebody is telling you this is my place
and like go away from here. I was I was
here and you tell him yes okay you know
what I will give you this area instead
of telling him no it's not your place
it's my place and you leave him you give
him the the the area then no wonder
he'll he'll fire rockets at you because
you already gave him the justice like
the the Arabs in Gaza they think they
are right
>> it was time to speak to someone from
Hamas
as an elected politician and the wife of
a prominent martyr
I asked Mrs. Mansour about Hamas's
political role.
Everyone I've met believes their right.
Of course, Palestinians deserve peace
and equal rights,
and violence against Israelis is
unacceptable.
But many Jews I've encountered while
making this film don't seem to
understand the precursors to this
violence against them.
Almost 90 years ago, resistance to
disproportionate power was already well
underway.
Whereas the Jews are armed and since
they wish ill of the Arabs and every
time an Arab falls into their hands they
attack him. And whereas the government
protects them, discriminates in their
favor and instructs them to denigrate
the law. For all these reasons, I
request to bear arms.
>> Flames were found again as the Jewish
agency suggested an idea.
Transfer of at least a fifth of the Arab
population to Trans Jordan.
By 1937,
Jews formed a third of the population of
Palestine, and the idea of population
transfer soon took root,
its legacy lingering.
>> I have a lot of Palestinian friends that
live abroad and they can't come and
visit because they don't have the status
to come and visit. they don't have the
right passport to to enter uh what we
call Israel uh Palestine and uh and then
you find out that there is a lot of
Ethubians and any any other origin
country they can come and visit and live
in Israel
>> when the Jews came from Ethiopia country
celebrated it was like it was it was a
great festival here when the Jews
finally were able to come from Russia
everybody was so happy to have them
The fact that any diaspora Jew or part
Jew can move to Israel where diaspora
Palestinians have no such right is a key
stumbling block to peace.
But I keep coming back to walls and
checkpoints because as a Jew I find
these particularly troubling given our
own history of being walled in by
others.
Let's take Gaza for example. It's pretty
much a ghetto these days and we've built
a wall around it.
Gaza is not a ghetto. Gaza is where
Arabs live.
We left Gaza in 2005.
What did they do? They continued
shelling us. We don't want to fence
ourselves in. We don't want to fence
them out if they would be not violent.
>> We don't want to die just to satisfy
someone's whim that a people which we
don't believe is a people should have
our homeland. That's not on the table.
>> When Jews heard Arab leaders saying,
"I'm going to wipe Israel out of the map
of the earth," one needs to understand
what happens to a Jew when he hears
that. I think that the Jews have a very
strong post-traumatic
uh memory from the Holocaust.
Jews are becoming very defensive to a
point where they say no more. Now we
will defend oursel and sometime that
defense is very strong
due to history.
There's no doubt that the Gaza story is
a very big ghetto of people being
trapped without hope, without dreams.
But I don't think that the Jews are
waking up in the morning and just say,
"I'm going to lock them in this ghetto
because they're Arabs or Muslims."
>> 6 million Jews were killed in the
Holocaust. So, I understand the Jewish
reaction.
Although, I want to believe that Jews
are better than this. That we can
overcome our fears or at least
recontextualize them, allowing us to
face fresh situations, clearsighted
rather than an eternal defensiveness.
The world changed as the Nazis rose.
My immediate family was lucky enough to
have left mainland Europe before the
Holocaust, although most of my American
grandparents' families were still there
when Hitler began exterminating Jews.
People like my great uncle Gerson
Serotaa, a famous caner known as the
Jewish Caruso, who'd even performed at
Carnegie Hall.
He and his family died in the Warsaw
Ghetto uprising.
>> My grandpa, he had an uncle that during
World War II, he was a partisan fighting
against the Nazis and uh there were the
story says that there were gypsies who
telling who were telling information of
where he is and uh then they killed him.
>> On my mother's side of the family, most
of her uh aunts and uncles did not make
it out of the Holocaust.
After centuries of persecution, the
Holocaust has left an open wound on the
psyche of Jews.
This is why Jews of all people need to
be so careful not to repeat history's
cycles.
Many Palestinians expressed sympathy,
but asked why Muslims of Palestine
should be more humanitarian than the
world's Christians.
The Holocaust is just just like the the
top the peak of the mountain of of
killing Jews industrially.
Like non-Jews, Christians specifically
more than more than Muslims. Also
Muslims, but more Christians has killed
Jews since forever.
It's worth reiterating that it is the
Christian world, not Muslims, who are
overwhelmingly responsible for the mass
slaughter of Jews over the last thousand
years.
In contrast, our relations with Muslims
had largely been good,
with science proving a closer
relationship than many like to admit.
Jews who don't believe the Palestinians
have any right to any of the Holy Land
claim their relative newcomers,
arriving with Muslim hordes around 636
AD.
But a number of DNA studies from
University College London to NYU Medical
Center to the University of Hifa and
more have concluded the same thing.
Many Jews and Palestinians share common
genetic Canaanite heritage, making this
story even more tragic.
>> It really harms me to know that the
oppressed oppresses even harder.
People who has faced such painful agony
through the Holocaust should not be
doing the same to other humans.
I really feel sorry for the Jews, but
does that give them the right to take
over my homeland? I don't think so.
In 1944,
when it came to the Holy Land, Zionists
had lost their British political backing
with Britain now refusing to admit fresh
immigrants, just as Jewish interest in
immigrating rocketed thanks to the
Holocaust.
So groups like Irun issued a declaration
of war against the British, who they
wanted out, initiating a long campaign
of violence, just as the Allies emerged
from World War II victorious.
But victory cost Britain dear, and there
was a new sense of purpose in their
rhetoric on Palestine, as expressed to
the prime minister.
If we are not prepared to maintain law
and order in Palestine, then it will be
better to get out.
Thank you.
When I came into office, I promised to
look at the world's challenges
with open eyes and very fresh thinking.
I have determined that it is time to
officially recognize Jerusalem as the
capital of Israel.
I've judged this course of action to be
in the best interests of the United
States of America
and the pursuit of peace between Israel
and the Palestinians.
When Donald Trump announced Jerusalem is
the capital of Israel, he was dealing
with this as a deal. the life of people
and the rights of people and the human
rights of people is not a deal that you
can negotiate on a table for u take it
or leave it.
>> If America's recent approach to peace
isn't working, who does need to take the
lead negotiation role?
Someone has to.
Historically, this level of
disenfranchisement has always led to
revolution.
In 1946,
as the race towards statehood
accelerated, there was another
unforeseen casualty.
Jews who'd lived peacefully for
centuries across the Arab world were
being forced to leave as Palestinian
resentment against Zionist actions
spread.
Then violence reached new heights.
>> Jerusalem has long been the focal point
of the still unsolved problem of
Palestine. In the Holy Land, violence
continues. Members of underground
organizations blow up the Cairo Hifa
Express, carrying 250 British troops
among its passengers. The heavy blast
kills eight and injures 41, smashing the
wooden coaches to kindling wood.
>> Five Britons die and six more are
injured as a blast wrecks police
headquarters at Serona near Tel Aviv in
Palestine. The terrific
>> The gloves were off as Zionist terrorism
against Britain accelerated.
It's estimated there were almost 50
incidents, many deadly, in the first
half of 1946 alone. But the King David
Hotel bombing plumbed new depths.
The King David Hotel itself, it was in
the wing on the right of the picture
that the terrorists placed their
explosive. The hotel housed the British
Army headquarters and the Palestine
government offices, and casualties were
very heavy.
65 deaths are reported and there is
little or no hope of survival for any of
the 58 missing. Nearly 50 others were
injured. The Jewish terrorist
organization vi openly admitted
responsibility for the bombing. Many
arrests have been made.
Violence had become entrenched and many
British politicians now saw the Balffor
Declaration as a colossal blunder.
Even Winston Churchill had changed his
mind. The cost to Britain was too high.
A sentiment echoed by Hugh Dalton.
The present state of affairs is not only
costly to us in manpower and money, but
is of no real value from the strategic
point of view. You cannot in any case
have a secure base on top of a wasp's
nest.
>> Having created this wasps nest, the
British were now in full retreat.
Partition was suggested.
Zionists accepted while Palestinians
refused to share what they still saw as
their land.
On November 29th, 1947, the UN's
proposal to divide the country passed.
Violence restarted immediately. Zionists
now in full pursuit.
People left their country dazed and
directionless, without homes or money,
falling ill or dying while wandering
place to place.
There are two possibilities. A holy war,
jihad on a national scale, or the Arabs
would fight as isolated terrorist cells
as in Ireland.
>> Anoir Nusebbe felt that war had caught
Palestine's Arabs disorganized and
leaderless, its politicians incompetent,
corrupt, and treasonous, while British
rule had weakened the Arabs and
strengthened the Jews.
By May 1948, Zionist paramilitary groups
like Hagana and Urggon had conquered
Tiberius, Safed and Hifer.
Benorian called Hifer a frightening and
fantastic site,
a dead city, a Carryan city without a
living soul.
It's estimated that 3/4 of a million
Arabs fled or were expelled from
Palestine during this period.
They call it the Nagba,
the catastrophe.
And together with post-holocaust
immigration, the Nagba radically changed
the country's demographics
with Jews forming almost half of the
population,
a tfold increase in less than 30 years.
Can we even imagine what such a seismic
population shift would feel like
anywhere in the world today?
The British left Palestine in 1948.
eight, leaving a new state of Israel
with shaky foundations, entrenched
patterns of violence and divisions which
persist to this day.
Mrs. Mansour's husband Jamal was killed
by Israeli defense forces along with
other leaders of Hamas after making a
widely publicized statement that he
supported an end to terror attacks and
that they should give peace talks a
chance.
living now the dayto-day crossing into
like the checkpoint doing all these
things you I don't know if this is what
they want us to feel but for me
personally as mice I don't feel any hope
I'm actually very scared for the future
>> no future
no future
>> we like to be peace in the international
and in the Middle East without to give
something for Palestine people. No
peace.
>> Do we actually want peace enough to stop
pointing fingers at the other?
>> I'm not very optimistic for the future.
I believe in the power of people uh
creating connections and changing but
not in the power of governments to do
that. Not even in the power in the will
of governments to do that.
>> The problem is the trust you know all
the problem is a trust. I see a a big
difference between what a Jewish person
is doing, let's say, in Europe, and I
support his right to self-deter
self-determination, his right to
equality, his right to live as a Jewish
person wherever he wants. But do I
support the right of a Jewish person to
live as a superior being to my existence
in Palestine? No. That's not something I
sympathize with. And that's not
something that's not something I
sympathize with and that's not something
I would ever accept.
>> This conflict has already spread across
the world. From Palestinians forced to
flee to those communities where they've
made their new homes to families like
mine who argue constantly about the
actions of the Israeli state to its
international critics and the cries of
anti-semitism made by some Jews to
deflect discussion of Israel's policies.
Surely the sooner we face and address
legitimate concerns,
the sooner we can all move forward.
>> Well, I could see peace happening
as soon as the people start to put
themselves in the other person's shoes.
We won't have peace before that.
>> The solution for the problem here is
really simple. Like what's the solution
for racism? End of racism. What's the
solution for oppression? End of
oppression.
So the solution is really simple. How to
get there? That's something I do not
know. How we will never ever get there.
That's something I know.
We have governments around the world
that support the oppression of the
Israeli regime, supports Palestinians
way means of surviving that oppression.
So these governments around the world
continue to support two sides of the
exact same problem. The rational outcome
of such kind of behavior is maintaining
the problem rather than resolving the
problem.
>> I've witnessed a clear disparity of
lifestyle and opportunity between Jew
and Arab in the Holy Land, which is a
direct legacy from history.
Equal human rights are a necessity
within these borders for open democracy.
And from what I've seen, the rising
number of settlements and continued
violence by factions on both sides make
the internationally supported two-state
solution seem remote.
I began this journey looking for answers
and the people I've met have given me
plenty to think about. Israel, Muna,
Issa, and Kobe have different views on
what comes next.
When that time of the Messiah comes, the
messianic age, when Isaiah says that the
lamb will lie down with the lion,
my teacher told me, even then I would
rather be the lion rather than the lamb.
>> We live it day by day. I don't know if a
car passes by and it has some people
whom the Israelis are targeting and they
are going to bomb. I I just cannot judge
what's going to come tomorrow.
>> Palestinians should do much better than
what they are doing now. We need to do a
election. We need to choose a new
leadership, young leadership, smart
leadership, and not to sell ourselves to
anybody else on the ground.
I think the majority of the Israelis,
they want peace, but they are controlled
by their fear and controlled by their
leadership. If we don't stop Israeli
right-wing government from going on with
their settlement expansion and with
their military intervention in West
Bank, I think we will have very dark
dark future. Palestinians are victims of
war. Jews are victims of holocaust and
we can do a competition who is more of a
victim.
But the thing about self victimizing is
that you surround yourself with walls. I
think that if Israeli and Palestinians
would really have a meaningful dialogue,
if we would talk,
you could listen and have sympathy for
the other side's tragedy.
>> Listen to the other. Treat the other
well.
Clearly virtues that were often missing
throughout this history.
Collectively, our actions have had
consequences, killing tens of thousands
of people over a century and displacing
millions more.
And distorting or whitewashing history
has just made it harder to untangle the
problem.
There's obviously a huge disparity in
the viewpoints I've encountered. So at
times I found my journey harrowing as
stereotypes and my own preconceptions
have shattered.
But I've also found hope. If we follow a
universal spiritual principle, treating
others as we want to be treated
ourselves. I now believe that things
could be different.
Any
solution
would need uh to recognize
all parties of the conflict. Not
controlled by anybody, just my rights
and my duties and the others rights and
the others duties.
>> Do you have any empathy at all for the
Palestinian position?
>> No, I have no empathy at all for the
Palestinian position. It's not like
something I'm ashamed of. To me, there's
no such thing as a Palestinian. It's a
big lie.
>> Do you see any parallels between your
perception of the others and the Jews
being cast as the others throughout
history?
Violence hasn't worked in the last 100
years, and it isn't working now.
But this is a new generation and we
don't have to create further conflict
moving forward.
If we want something different, it's
time to take collective responsibility
for our inherited roles in this saga.
To respect the other and to say enough
is enough.
I think everybody in Israel that when
he's literally said when you grow up
there won't be an army and you won't be
needed as a soldier. I I can say that it
is a hope
>> to the future. We want to live with the
Spani and the beast.
>> Well, I'm a Jew and therefore my hopes
for the future are always for the
complete redemption of the entire world.
I do have a better hope for the future
especially because now I have a little
girl, a little kid that I want her to
live a better life than I did. Um I want
her to live a normal life and for that
to happen um peace needs to happen.
>> When I become a little bit adult, you
know, not a motivated Israeli brainwash,
I actually understand
that there is a Palestinians and there
is Israeli. There is one land and both
sides want their own country.
>> We have to have our own state and our
own independent state. Feel very
connected here to everything to to the
country
like uh you know we came home
>> as King Solomon says nothing new under
the sun.